<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anthony Paint[er] the blaspheming caryar Who sunke into the ground vp to the neck, and there stood two day[s and] two nights, and not to bee drawne out by the strength of hor[ses] or digged out by the help of man: and there dyed the 3. of Nouember. 1613. Also the punishment of Nicholas Mesle a most wicked blasphemer. Reade and tremble. Published by authoritie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08837</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120566</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855762</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855762</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21264</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08837)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21264)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 897:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anthony Paint[er] the blaspheming caryar Who sunke into the ground vp to the neck, and there stood two day[s and] two nights, and not to bee drawne out by the strength of hor[ses] or digged out by the help of man: and there dyed the 3. of Nouember. 1613. Also the punishment of Nicholas Mesle a most wicked blasphemer. Reade and tremble. Published by authoritie.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Eld] for Iohn Trundle: and are to be sold at Christ Church Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bracketed parts of title from STC; printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes: Briefes drawne out of the registers of the Court of Parliament.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ (-A1, C4).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page cropped, affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Blasphemy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Curiosities and wonders --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21264:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21264:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ANTHONY PAINT<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> THE <hi>Blaſpheming Caryar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who ſunke into the ground vp to the neck, and there stood two day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> two nights, and not to bee drawne out by the ſtrength of Hor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> or digged out by the help of man: and there dyed the 3. <hi>of Nouember.</hi> 1613.</p>
            <p>Alſo the puniſhment of <hi>Nicholas Meſle</hi> a moſt wicked blaſphemer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reade and tremble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authoritie.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>At London printed for <hi>Iohn Trundle:</hi> and are to be ſold at Chriſt Church Gate. 1614.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21264:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21264:2"/>
            <head>THE <hi>STRANGE PVNISH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT</hi> AND IVDGEMENT OF GOD, VPON A CVRSED blaſphemer: ANTHONY PANETER Caryer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Remble all yee people, ſtoope now and fall downe vnder the dreadfull and moſt iuſt Iudgement of that great <hi>Iehouah,</hi> which holdes in his hand, Heauen, Earth, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing that therein is, weighing them in ſcales as though it were duſt: Bee now amazed at the might of ſo mighty an arme, which in the twinck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an eye cruſheth and beateth downe ſinners in his wrath, ſcattereth them as the winde doth the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppers, and maketh them the ſubiect and argument of his glorie, in the ſight of all Nations. O fearefull iudgements of the moſt High, which ſuffers not his glorie to be troden vnder foote, but when hee thinkes fit brings the iuſt and horrible plagues of his auenge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vpon the deſpiſer of his holy Name. How ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and full of horrour, quoth the Pſalmiſt, it is to fall into the Lords hands, when hee puts on the armour and weapons of his wrath; as the holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> ſheweth in the tenth Chapter of the Epiſtle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes, he may when he pleaſes puniſh with diuers pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments
<pb facs="tcp:21264:3"/> and temporall plagues, beſides the eternall damnation thoſe that rebell againſt him and offend his ſacred Maieſtie. Tremble and ſhake againe (O Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners) (for the Prophet <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the 14. of <hi>Exodus</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth vnto you the decree from heauen ſo dire and frightfull, ſaying, that this great God without vſing the miniſterie or meanes of any man ſendeth his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels (the executioners of his vengeance) againſt the proud profane which ſets light by his holy Name; That high minded <hi>Nabuchodonoſor</hi> King of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon ſhall bee, though to his great ſhame, the firſt wee will produce for an enſample to all poſteritie. <hi>Pharao</hi> King of Egypt, and the ten notable plagues, which, the ſame God, auenging his honour, did ſend vppon that ſwaggering ſpirit, are euident proofes of the ſame; waters turned into bloud, filthy Frogges, Lice, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance of Flies, the mortalitie of men by peſtilence, murren and death of Cattell, Boyles and Scabbes, Haile, and frighting Thunders, Graſhoppers, obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and palpable darkneſſe, briefely the very Angell of the ſame God whom he blaſphemed made warre againſt him, yea' by things that ſeemed very contemptible and of no force; by the onely winde of his mouth and by his deſtroying Angell he ouerthrowes and quite vndoes the proud and inſolent blaſphemer <hi>Senacherib</hi> King of the Aſſyrians, for attempting with blaſphemous words to ſpite this Soueraigne God, but the ſame moſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God made him well knowe and all men after him, that it is he that puniſheth and ſheweth mercie, which killeth and keepeth aliue, which makes wonders in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, and hee throweth e'en downe to the ground that loftie man, by the hands of <hi>Sarazar</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dramalec</hi> his owne Children, within the temple of his owne falſe God <hi>Nezrok</hi> in Niniuie: And as the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:21264:3"/> our great God hath diuers and ſundry wayes at hand, ſo doth he diuerſly inflict and layeth paines vpon ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: ſometimes by the Elements, as <hi>Moſes</hi> witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in the 26 of <hi>Leuit.</hi> and 11. of <hi>Deuteronomie.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by ſickneſſes of ſundry ſorts. <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. Sometimes by the Sword and by Warre. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 5. Sometimes by Famine, by Fire, by Captiuitie, briefly in a thouſand manners when it pleaſeth him to take re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge for his honour offended: night cannot hide the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners from him: their ſtrength and nimblenes of their bodie cannot ſaue them: Monarkes, Emperours, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Kings doe tremble and ſhake vnder his mightie hand: the ſtrongeſt, and beſt fortreſſes tumble bowne at his onely looke: It is that terrible and potent God, of whom ſpake that Captaine of the Hebrues, <hi>Iudas Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabeus,</hi> who is like in force and greatnes to the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God of the Hebrues? and the ſame poſie hee vſed in his enſignes of war. Doe you think then you wretched and accurſed blaſphemers of the Name of the moſt High (at whoſe terrible lookes the earth doth tremble, the elements do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, the heauen fadeth away, and the ſea flyeth out) doe you thinke (ſay I to you) doe yee thinke to ſhunne the furie of his face, and eſcape the heauines of his arme that can not be auoided; O accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed blaſphemers, the firſt and cheefeſt, more wicked and more abhominable than all other ſinners, doe you not ſée, that as many times as you open your ſtincking mouthes to blaſpheme the Name of the Almighty, as many times the Diuels and frightfull fiends doe enter within your ſelues through euery blaſphemie? Doeſt thou beléeue wretched blaſphemer, that God which ſéeth and vnderſtandeth thee is deafe or a ſleepe, or elſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted and buſie about ſome other buſines, like the Idols of the Paynims, as the holy Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> did
<pb facs="tcp:21264:4"/> in old time, reproach vnto the Idolaters of thoſe dayes? Doſt thou thinke thou muſt neuer be called to accompt, for thy foule and ſtinking blaſphemies, bee it neuer ſo late, that letting looſe the reines of thy deſolate tongue, which polluteth both heauen and earth, thou ſhalt thus ſtill liue without God, without Faith, and Religion in this world? Thou art, O blaſphemer! farre worſe and more wicked than a Theefe, a Niggard, a Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, a Lyar, a Whooremonger, a Wanton, an Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, a Drunkard, a Glutton, an Idolater, a Ruffian and Pandar, or a Conceaier of ſt althes: for thou art traiterous and rebellious vnto God, ſpitting in his face as many times as thou blaſphem'ſt againſt his holy Name, with no leſſe indignitie and ignominie, than the Iewes which did buffet and ſpit vpon the bleſſed Sauiour of the world. And if Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid in the ſixt to the Hebrues, that ſinners do crucifie once againe the Sonne of God, that being ſaid in generall how much more in particular may it be applyed to the Swearers and Blaſphemers of the Name of God.</p>
            <p>For, thoſe (as ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) doe not ſin leſſe, which blaſpheme our Sauiour Chriſt, raigning in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, than thoſe which haue crucified him walking vpon the earth: Yea it may be ſaid, that it is leſſe ſinne to blaſpheme Ieſus Chriſt hanging and dying on the Croſſe, than now he is ſitting and raigning in heauen, liuing, and triumphing. The Iewes, not knowing that he was the Sonne of God, did blaſpheme and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily beſpit him; but now blaſphemers, that know him to be the very Sonne of God, doe yet worſe than euer the Iewes did, and are yet more wicked than the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned which blaſpheme God, in that by blaſphemies they make this world their very Hell, by anticipation; It is moſt certainely held amongſt the Diuines, that
<pb facs="tcp:21264:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> God is nothing ſo angry for the blaſphemies of all the damned altogether, as for the blaſphemie of one blaſphemer aliue, for blaſphemie is not forbidden to the damned: on the contrarie as the glorie of the Saints in heauen is to praiſe and bleſſe GOD, ſo is it a puniſhment and torment to the damned to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme him: but vnto the liuing it is moſt expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forbidden to ſpeake blaſphemie, vpon paine of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall damnation: whence it followeth as it is aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid that the blaſphemers, what pretence and colour ſoeuer they will couer their accurſed ſwearing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, are worſe and more wicked than the damned, and are like to this Monſter fained by <hi>Homer,</hi> expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>Lucretius</hi> in this verſe,
<q>Prima Leo, poſtrema draco, media ipſa Chymera.</q>
            </p>
            <p>A true Hyerogliphick or poeſie of the wretched blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers, ſwaggering like Lyons, venemous like Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, and no leſſe abhominable diuerſe and counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet in the framing their blaſphemies, than theſe <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meraes</hi> hideous and inuented Monſters; But that wee may not ſtay ouerlong in the choiſe and picking out of the iuſt iudgements and plagues inflicted and vſed by the great GOD from time to time vppon blaſphemers, wee will inſiſt vpon one onely example among many, being an accident of freſh memorie and aboue all other moſt exemplarie, worthy to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and remembred, in all ages; Set before your eyes this notable and dreadfull example of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment lately executed by the Diuine vengeance vppon one named <hi>Anthony Paneter,</hi> an ordinarie Carrier in the territorie named <hi>La Condamina,</hi> three leagues di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from the Cittie of, <hi>Genoa</hi> in Italy: This man returning from the Cittie with two horſes loaden with diuers wares, and his horſes for the heauines of their
<pb facs="tcp:21264:5"/> burthen ſcarcely able to goe faſt inough to bee at home afore night, fell vnto ſuch chafing and rage, that cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, banning, blaſpheming deſpitefully, and with a deſperate madnes the holy and fearefull Name of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, calling the Diuell to come to help him, or elſe that hee ſhould carrie him away and his horſes withall (as, alas! it is to ordinarie an vſe of ſome Car-men, and Carriers both by Sea and by Land euery foote to blaſpheme and curſe the holy Name of GOD) this vile wretch not ceaſing his furie on a ſudden was ſtricken with the reuenging hand of him againſt whom hée did ſo outragiouſly vomit his blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies; for beeing about two leagues forward on his way, ſtill continuing his outragious curſing, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and blaſpheming, The earth mooued and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at the very horrour of his oathes and blaſphemies would not, nor yet could any further beare and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine ſo vile a Monſter, but at the will and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Creatour opened it ſelfe, and gaped vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the feete of that vile wretch, and ſwallowed him vp to the necke, ſo that hee could by no meanes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer himſelfe from thence. Stay now and behold yee bloudie blaſphemers, and deteſtable ſwearers; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip heere in feare and trembling, the Maieſtie and power of him againſt whom your voice ſpeakes, and your tongue vtters ſuch vile oathes and fearefull cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; Let this wretch bee an example vnto you of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, leauing that filthy and damnable cuſtome, whileſt you haue time, &amp; whilſt yet God ſtayes his hand to call you vnto repentance &amp; amendment. This wretch thus ſtricken with the hand of God, his two horſes ſtill followed their way vntil they came home; his wife ſeeing the horſes thus come without their vnfortunate maiſter was inſtantly taken with great feare and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:21264:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> leaſt that her huſband ſhould be ſlaine or robbed vpon the way by ſome théeues or others, ſo ſhe ſtayed a little ſtill looking for him, but hearing no newes of his comming, ſhe gets out of the houſe and goes all lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and dolefull along the highway towards the Citty of <hi>Genoa,</hi> accompanied with ſome friends or neighbours of hers, becauſe it was already late &amp; about thrée houres in the night. She went not farre but that ſhe found on the way one of her neighbours named <hi>Ambroſe Vidoze,</hi> of whom (all amazed and diſtracted as ſhe was) ſhe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked whence he came, he ſaid he came from <hi>Genoa;</hi> ſhe further aſked him whether he had met with her huſband whereat yet all affrighted trembling and aſtoniſhed at the horrible and frightull cries of this miſerable Catiffe which he had heard, he told her that lately without ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him or any body hee did heare a voyce and dreadful crye vppon the way which ſaid in theſe wordes. I am damnd, I am damnd to all the diuels of hell, becauſe I haue ſo often and in ſo many faſhions ſworne and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed the holy name of God: Thus the poore <hi>Vidoze</hi> ſtricken with the terror of this fright could ſpeake no more, but went home; where caſting himſelfe on his bed he died ſodainly not able to ſpeake a word: a thing ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily at the which our hayres may ſtand vpright on our heads able to ſhake and amaze all our ſences.</p>
            <p>The woman with her company pittifully crying and tearing herſelfe, followes on her way and neuer leaues till they had found the ſaid <hi>Anthonie Panetier</hi> whoſe frightfull voice they heard a far off ſtil crying that he was damned with all the deuils in hell, becauſe he had ſo often and wickedly blaſphemed the holy Name of GOD; beſides that (a thing moſt wonderfull) hee was enuironed and aſſaulted by a troope of hungry and rauenous Wolues ready to deuoure him, had
<pb facs="tcp:21264:6"/> not ſome men with ſwords, ſtaues, peeces and ſhot ranne thither, and yet could ſcarce maiſter them, ſo raging were theſe beaſts againſt the man, as though they had beene ſent thither like ſo many Sergeants to execute the vengeance of the Almighty. That wicked wretch made no long ſtay there but hee was ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and cited before him whom hee had thus blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, for the next day hee was found dead, and yet could not bee drawne from thence. Such was the iudgement of the Diuine Maieſtie, againſt this wretch: Such was the end of the ſaid <hi>Painter,</hi> which ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine for an enſample vnto all curſing, ſwearing, banning, and blaſpheming perſons, which make but a ieſt and mockerie at euery word to bring an oath and teare and take at their pleaſure that great holy and dreadfull Name of Almightie GOD without any reuerence, or diſcretion; nay without any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, occaſion, anger, choller, or croſſe in the world; but through a moſt vile accurſed and deteſtable vſe and cuſtome they haue inured themſelues vnto, So that now a dayes (ſo depraued is this our age) a man thinketh to bee eſteemed more braue and more drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which at euery word can ſweare and trimme his ſpeech with oathes, taking and tearing GOD from the head to the foote, and if any hearer hauing horrour bee offended, or goes about to rebuke them, his returne ſhall be vile words, and oftentimes blowes.</p>
            <p>The holy Doctors of the Church agree all vppon this point and hold for certaine that all wickedneſſe, parricides, inceſts, poiſonings, murthers, and other crimes are nothing ſo great, neither deſerue ſuch pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment as doe blaſphemie, inaſmuch as all wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes (as the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaid) are at their firſt committed againſt men, but blaſphemies are firſt and
<pb facs="tcp:21264:6"/> directly againſt the honour of God, and e'en as it were to ſpight him.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Dathan, Corah,</hi> and <hi>Abiran</hi> for hauing mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mured againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> in the wilderneſſe, haue beene gulped vp and ſwallowed aliue with all their families into the deepeſt bowels of the earth, what muſt blaſphemers looke for and expect but the very ſame and worſe?</p>
            <p>If any back-biteth or ſpeaketh ill neuer ſo little of his King and Prince, hee is by and by chaſtned and put to an exemplarie death; Why ſhould not the blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer be vſed ſo, ſith that by his blaſphemie hee doth no leſſe then ſpit vpon the very face of God, which is the King of Kings, the Lord of Lords, and the Soueraigne Monark of all the world.</p>
            <p>If the Law of worldly Kings and Princes is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violably obſerued and executed againſt ſuch men, Why ſhall not Gods Law bee likewiſe put in execution, which expreſſely and vpon great threatnings doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Kings and Magiſtrates to put the blaſphemer to death, and to cut and roote him out from amongſt his people to appeaſe his anger?</p>
            <p>The ancient Romanes did ſo abhorre and deteſt a Blaſphemer, that finding no torments fit inough for his puniſhment they did giue him vp to the fury of their gods, after he had béen publikely whipped, cauſing this to be proclaimed before him.</p>
            <div type="examples">
               <pb facs="tcp:21264:7"/>
               <head>Doe not ſweare by the name of the Gods raſhly.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HEſiodus</hi> in the firſt booke of his daies and workes affirmeth, that in all ages the Blaſphemer hath beene bitterly puniſhed by the Gods (for hée was a Pagan and knew not the true God) and that the firſt Blaſphemers were laid out and ſet for a prey vnto Vultures, add rauenous birds to feede vpon, which did eate their eyes, tongue and Liuer; Alas! if theſe poore Heathen haue beléeued that their falſe Gods thus would, and did auenge their honour, how can we make any doubt beeing Chriſtians, but that the true God, which we worſhip, will puniſh the blaſphemers, ſith that he commands it to the Iudges and Magiſtrates of the earth without any reſtriction.</p>
               <p>The wiſe man in his Eccleſiaſticus chap. 13. ſaith that the man which vſeth to ſweare ſhall be filled with iniquitie and the plague and affliction ſhall not goe farre from his houſe.</p>
               <p>In the 12. chap. of Saint <hi>Mathew</hi> the blaſphemie of the Spirit ſhall not be pardoned, neither in this world, nor in the other. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in in his Reuelation, chap. 16. giues a reaſon for it, ſaying, that the damned ſhall chew their tongues for very ſmart and diſpaire, and for their plagues they ſhall blaſpheme the God of heauen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did not amend themſelues.</p>
               <p>The Théefe hideth himſelfe to ſteale: The Letcher ſeekes darknes out to commit his wickednes in, the proud counterfetteth himſelfe to bee humble, the enui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, the couetous, the glutton, and the idle, couer and
<pb facs="tcp:21264:7"/> draw out of mens ſight their vices; as being aſhamed of them, but the blaſphemer alone is a ſhameleſſe, ſawcie, wicked one, vttering publikely and without ſhame and feare his blaſphemies againſt the holy Name of God, nay thinkes it a meane to be eſteemed a braue and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant fellow, and ſo he is; but in the Diuels Schoole and in the academie of the damned and Reprobate, O how happie was the age of that great Doctor Saint <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi> In whoſe time blaſphemers were preſently pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and with great rigour, as it appeareth in his firſt Homily to the people of Antiochia, grounded vppon the places of Scripture there cited in theſe words: whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhall heare the voice of the blaſphemer if hee accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him not, he ſhall beare his iniquitie. <hi>Leu.</hi> 5. <hi>chap.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God ſaid vnto <hi>Moſes</hi> caſt out the blaſphemer out of the Campe, and let all the people ſtone him. <hi>Leu.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>In the ſame place God ſaith, The blaſphemer ſhall die the death; The ſame ſentence was executed vpon a blaſphemer, whoſe mother was an Iſraelite, and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Egyptian which was ſtoned to death in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iudas Machabeus</hi> for the ſame crime cauſed the tong of <hi>Nicanor</hi> to be cut and minced for foode to the birds of the ayre, <hi>Mac.</hi> 2. booke, laſt Chap.</p>
               <p>The blaſphemer of Corinth was deliuered to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell S. <hi>Paul.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor. chap.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nabuchodonoſor</hi> by a ſolemne Decree commanded that whoſoeuer ſhould blaſpheme the God of <hi>Daniel</hi> ſhould die the death? <hi>Dan. chap.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>The lawes of the Church <hi>Extr. de maledict. C. Statui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> thus condemne them, that whoſoeuer ſhall be found to haue blaſphemed the holy name of God, the Virgine <hi>Mary,</hi> or the Saints, muſt ſtand by ſeuen Sundaies at the Church doore and not goe in, and the laſt Sunday of
<pb facs="tcp:21264:8"/> them muſt be there barefoot, &amp; a halter about his neck; he refuſing to do ſo, hee muſt be thruſt out and ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Church and depriued of Chriſtian buriall.</p>
               <p>The ciuill and Imperiall law puniſheth them ſeuere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, decreeing that it is a greater ſin to blaſpheme the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Maieſty then the temporall or worldly Maieſty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phillip</hi> the faire <hi>alias le Bel,</hi> King of France decreed that blaſphemers ſhould be thrown into a riuer or poole.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robert</hi> King of France iudged them to death without pardon.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Lewis</hi> King of France would haue them marked in the forehead with a hot Iron and their tongue peirced through</p>
               <p>King <hi>Hnery</hi> the 3 likewiſe made an excellent ſtatute againſt them.</p>
               <p>The matter then being ſo weighty and of ſo high a conſequence as directly touching the honour of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God: Let all good and faithfull Chriſtians be vppon their knees holding vp their handes, and pouring out teares at the feet of our gracious Soueraigne Lord and King) whom God bleſſe with long and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py yeares) of his moſt wiſe counſell, and of the Lords of his iuſtice with moſt humble and deuout petition that by this notable example they would bee pleaſed better and better to put in execution the decree of God againſt blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers confirmed and obſerued from time to time through all lawes, Commonwealthes, and kingdomes, that thereby God being appeaſed for the ſinnes of this World, we may ſee vnder our King <hi>Lewis</hi> 13. and his moſt wiſe mother Regent a golden age, vice exiled, chaſtened, and extinguiſhed, vertue and Chriſtian faith exalted, that ſo our France may be a mirror of vertue, piety and iuſtice vnto other nations. So be it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="edict">
            <pb facs="tcp:21264:8"/>
            <head>Briefes drawne out of the Regiſters of <hi>the Court of Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon the motion and complaint made vnto the Court by the Kings Atturney generall, that as well in <hi>Paris</hi> as in other places, from whence notice was giuen to him by many of his Subſtitutes or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties in ſundry Shires, and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions or reſorts of <hi>Seneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaldoms</hi> and other Territories, amongſt the huge wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſes, and horrible impieties brought in through the vnbridled licentiouſnes of the ciuill warres, the Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies againſt the holy Name of God, of the bleſſed Virgin his mother, and the execrable oathes, deteſtable renouncings, abominable curſings and defyings or ſpigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of their names and power, are growne ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and familiar amongſt all perſons, of what conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo euer, that to appeaſe the ire and wrath of God, it is very neceſſarie to renew and bring in againe the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie as well of the auncient Statutes of the Kings <hi>S. Lewis:</hi> of <hi>Philip; Charles</hi> the 8. <hi>Lewes</hi> 12. <hi>Henry</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth: as alſo the Decrees and ordinances of the ſaid Court in the yeeres 1544 1572. and 1575. Requeſting that an order may therein be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Court, and that which herevpon ſhall bee or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by the ſame, ſhall be reade and proclaimed with a loude voice, in the high places and markets through the
<pb facs="tcp:21264:9"/> towne and Suburbs, likewiſe in all the Iuſtice-ſeates or Courts, as wel generall as particular of all the ſhires, Seneſchaldomes, and Prouoſtſhips of this reſort and power.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Court according to the former Orders and Decrees, did make, and makes inhibition, did forbid and forbids all perſons in generall of what ſtate qualitie or condition they bee, to ſweare and blaſpheme the holy Name of God, of the bleſſed Virgin his Mother, or his Saints, vpon the penalties in the ſaid Orders and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees enioined, and danger of life and death, if the caſe requireth it: hath enioined and enioines or commands all Vſhers, Sergeants and Officers of the Iuſtices, to take, arreſt, and carry vnto priſon inſtantly, all thoſe whom they ſhall finde blaſpheming, that the Law may goe ſpéedily vpon them, and they be made an enſample; and commands all perſons which ſhall heare them ſwear to denounce and accuſe them to the Magiſtrates, adiud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging therefore to the Denonciators or Promotours the third part of the fines fined vpon them.</p>
            <p>And this preſent decrée ſhall bee read and proclaimed, which the ſound of the Trumpet, and publicke cry by the markets and high places of this Towne and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burbs, and places vſed and ordinarie for cries and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations: Alſo through all the Cities, Townes, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs, Villages, Shires, Seneſcaldomes and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoſt-ſhips of this reſort and power; Enioined and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to all Iudges of Prouinces to keep a ſtraight hand, and employ their power for the execution of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, and to the Subſtitutes of the ſaid Atturney gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to take all the courſes and orders therevnto neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, vpon penaltie of forfetting their Office. Done in Parliament the 26. <hi>Ianuarie</hi> 1613. And read and proclaimed with trumpets ſounding and publike crie
<pb facs="tcp:21264:9"/> through the high places and Markets of this Towne and Subburbs of <hi>Paris</hi> the 27. of the ſaid Moneth;</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed <hi>Voyſin.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="decree">
            <head>A Decree and Iudgement of the ſaid <hi>Court againſt</hi> Nicholas le Meſle <hi>Blaſphemer.</hi>
            </head>
            <figure/>
            <p>THe Court hauing ſeene and viewed the proceſſe cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall or euidence made by the Seneſcall of
<pb facs="tcp:21264:10"/> Mayne, or his<note n="a" place="margin">A Iudge to to ſit vpon life and death.</note> Lieutenant criminal in the territorie of Mans, at the ſute of the Subſtitute of the Kings At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turney generall Complainant and accuſer, againſt <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas le Meſle</hi> Priſoner in the priſons of the<note n="b" place="margin">As the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Gatehouſe.</note> Concier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie (or Ward) of the Palace hauing appealed (or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained) of the ſentence giuen againſt him by the ſaid Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſcall or his Lieutenant the 14. of May 1598. by the which ſentence for publicke amends and reparation of the caſes in the ſaid proceſſe mentioned and prooued, the ſaid <hi>Meſle</hi> was condemned to make the amends (called) honourable bare head, and bare foote, holding in his hand a burning Torch of two pounds weight before the great Portall and chiefe gate of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiall Church of Saint <hi>Peter;</hi> of the ſaid Towne of <hi>Mans,</hi> and there ſhall ſay publikely, and with a loude voice, that raſhly and maliciouſly hee had blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med againſt the Name of GOD, of whom hee cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued pardon of the King and his Iuſtice, this beeing done, bee baniſhed from the Country and Countie of Maine for fiue yeeres, and in that while forbidden to bee found there, vpon the penaltie in the Kings Statutes; and beſides condemned in two crownes fine to the King, and two crownes for the poore.</p>
            <p>The priſoner hauing beene heard and examined vpon the cauſes of his appeale and vpon the caſes laid on his charge hauing heard alſo the Kings Atturney generall which as for caſe newly comming to his knowledge had himſelfe declared to appeale <hi>a minima</hi> of the ſaid ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, requeſting to bee admitted to his appeale (as well prouided) and therevpon and vpon his concluſions (or demands) to haue right and Law; All beeing conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, It is ſaid or decréed that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the appeale de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the ſaid <hi>Meſle,</hi> that he did appeale ill and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out greeuance, and ſhall be fined for: The Court hath
<pb facs="tcp:21264:10"/> receiued and doth receiue the Atturney generall to his appeale, <hi>a minima</hi> from the ſaid ſentence, admitted, and admits it (as well prouided) and doing right vpon the ſame, hath annihilated and annihilats both appeale and ſentence from the which he appealed, without fine; And for the caſes contained in the proces (or euidences) hath condemned and condemns the ſaid <hi>le Meſle,</hi> to doe the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend (called) honorable before the chiefe gate of our Ladies church of <hi>Paris,</hi> barefoote, and bare head, in his Shirt, a halter about his neck, holding in his hands a burning Torch of Waxe of two pounds weight, and there on his knees to ſay and declare that wickedly and maliciouſly he hath ſpoken and vttered the execrable blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies againſt the holy Name of God, and of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> whereof he repenteth and craued pardon of GOD, of the King and his Iuſtice; That beeing done, ſhall his tongue bee pearced through with a hot iron, and his two lippes ſlit or clouen, and afterwards hath baniſhed and does baniſh him from the Kingdome of <hi>France</hi> for euermore; hath enioyned him to keep and obſerue his baniſhment vppon penaltie where he ſhall bee found to bee hanged to death without any other proceſſe: hath declared and declares all his goods done and confiſcated to the K ng, taking firſt vppon them the ſumme of a hundreth crownes to bee applyed for the bread of the Priſoners of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciergie of the Pallace. Ordaineth that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe and euidence (on the which followed this decrée) ſhall be burned.</p>
            <p>The Court alſo makes inhibitions and forbids all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of what qualitie or condition ſoeuer they bee to ſweare &amp; blaſpheme the Name of God vpon the penaltie contained in the Statutes and decrees formerly made,
<pb facs="tcp:21264:11"/> And this preſent Decree ſhall be reade in the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate of Mans in the Siſes time, and when they are ſitting, at the ſute and ſolicitation of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of the Atturney generall in that place.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Pronounced to the ſaid <hi>le Meſle,</hi> and executed <date>the 27. of <hi>Ianuarie</hi> 1613.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Signed. <hi>Voyſin.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Tranſlated out of French: and printed at <hi>Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21264:11"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
